Enrique Riverón
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Enrique Riverón papers
1918-1990s
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Riverón, Enrique
3.3 linear feet
The papers of Enrique Riverón measure 3.3 linear feet and date from 1918-1990s. The collection contains correspondence, writings, diary entries, scrapbooks, printed material, and photographs documenting Riverón's career as an illustrator, cartoonist, painter and sculptor in the United States and Cuba and, to a lesser extent, Riverón's teaching career at Wichita University in Kansas.
Biographical Note
Painter, sculptor, cartoonist, and illustrator Enrique Riverón was born in 1902 in Cienfuegos, Cuba and belonged to the first generation of Cuban modernists, experimenting with Cubism and pursuing abstraction from very early on in his career. During his early twenties Riverón traveled to France, Italy, Belgium, and Spain to study under scholarships and attend the Academia de San Fernando in Madrid. In 1926 Riverón's first major one-man exhibition took place at the Association Paris Amerique Latine where the catalog introduction was written by noted Mexican writer Alfonso Reyes.
In 1927 Riverón returned to Havana and had a one-man show of his European work at the Asociación de Pintores y Escultores, as well as several other shows in Havana and New York. He moved to the United States in 1930 and became a United States citizen in 1943.
In addition to being known for his naturalistic drawings of street life in Paris and Cuba, Riverón began working with collage in the 1930s and was, for a number of years, a cartoonist for newspapers in Havana and other publications such as The New Yorker and Cine Mundial which was published in New York and widely circulated in Latin America. He also worked in Hollywood for a time as an illustrator for Walt Disney Pictures.
From 1940 on, Riverón focused on painting and sculpture. He moved to Miami from Wichita, Kansas, in 1964. Enrique Riverón died in 1998.
Scope and Content Note
The Enrique Riverón papers measure 3.3 linear feet, date from 1918-1990s and document Riverón's career as an illustrator, cartoonist, painter and sculptor in the United States and Cuba and, to a lesser extent, his teaching career at Wichita University in Kansas. The collection includes correspondence, the majority of which concerns Riverón's exhibitions; writings, primarily Riverón's recollections of his trips to Paris and Madrid and his memories of people he met in Latin America, Europe, and the United States; printed material documenting exhibitions and Riverón's work for magazines such as Cine-Mudial and Bally-Hoo; and photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into eight series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1929-1960 (box 1, 2 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1918-1991 (box 1, 0.6 ft.)
Series 3: Writings, 1923-1980s, undated (box 1, 0.2 ft.)
Series 4: Scrapbooks, 1920s-1990s, undated (boxes 1, 3, and 4, 0.7 ft.)
Series 5: Artwork, 1958-1983, undated (boxes 1 and 5, 0.4 ft.)
Series 6: Printed Material, circa 1930-1992 (boxes 2 and 5, 0.7 ft.)
Series 7: Photographs, 1918-1992, undated (boxes 2, 5 and 6, 0.6 ft.)
Series 8: Miscellany, 1927-1989, undated (box 6, 7 folders)
Related Material
The Archives of American Art also has a collection of Enrique Riverón letters to Mario Carreño, 1981-1990, in which Riverón writes of their mutual friends, his memories of Cuba, health issues, politics, pricing paintings, collages, and his longings for Paris and New York.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms.
Subjects:
Bermúdez, Cundo, 1914-; Baker, Josephine, 1906-1975; Carreño, Mario -- Photographs; Cantinflas, 1911-; Cugat, Xavier, 1900- -- Photographs; García Lorca, Federico, 1898-1936; Orozco, José Clemente, 1883-1949 -- Photographs; Kiki, 1901-1953; Milland, Ray -- Photographs; Neruda, Pablo, 1904-1973 -- Photographs; Peláez, Amelia, 1897-1968 -- Photographs; Picasso, Pablo, 1881-1973; Pidgeon, Walter, 1897-; Reed, Alma M. -- Photographs; Russell, Rosalind -- Photographs; Sicre, Juan José -- Photographs; Siqueiros, David Alfaro -- Photographs; Tamayo, Rufino, 1899- -- Photographs; Waguermert, Luis Gomez -- Photographs; Wichita State University -- Faculty
Subjects-Topical:
Artists -- Florida -- Miami; Cuban American artists; Expatriate artists -- Florida -- Miami; Artists -- Cuba; Cuban American art; Cartoonists; Caricatures and cartoons; Magazine illustration; Illustrators; Sculptors -- Florida -- Miami
Types of Materials:
Scrapbooks; Photographs
Names:
Gattorno, Antonio; Carreño, Mario; De Diego, Julio, 1900-; Gómez Sicre, José; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Lozano Castro, Alfredo; Prohias, Antonio; Rebajes, Pauline; Salinas, Baruj; Yunkers, Adja, 1900-
Provenance
The Enrique Riverón papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Patricia Riverón Lee, daughter of Riverón, in 1996.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, circa 1929-1960, Series 1:; (box 1, 2 folders)
  - Membership Cards, 1936-1944 (Box 1)
  - Diary Pages, circa 1929-1960 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1918-1991, undated, Series 2:; (box 1, 0.6 ft.)
  Correspondence found in this series is with artists and others including Mario Carreño, Julio de Diego, Antonio Gattorno, Alfredo Lozano, Antonio Prohias, Pauline and Frank Rebajes, Baruj Salina, José Gómez Sicre, Adja Yunkers, and others. Much of the correspondence concerns Riverón's exhibitions. Folders may contain letters, postcards, and related material to and/or from Riverón.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by individual or subject with one folder at the end of the series from a group of individuals concerning a publication.
  - Antonio, José, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Arroyo, Ramon, 1935, 1962-1984 (Box 1)
  - Badá, José Manuel, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Bens, José M., Colegio de Arquitectos de Cuba en el Exilio, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Carreño, Mario, 1941-1990, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Casado, Antonio F., 1945 (Box 1)
  - Casado, Juan José M., 1950-1982, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Casagrán, Jesús M., 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Cecilia, Román and Jermaine, 1953-1991 (Box 1)
  - Chávez, Camilio G., Lte. Colonel Jefe del Cuerpo de Aviació, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Dale ?, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Davidson, John, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Davila, Alberto, 1961, 1965 (Box 1)
  - De Diego, Julio, 1935-1977 (Box 1)
  - Delhart, Adria (Riverón's first wife), 1926 (Box 1)
  - Exhibitions (letters concerning), 1927-1990, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Fernandez, Antonio, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Galeria Sudamericana, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Garcia, Leandro, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Garmendia, Andrés, 1962-1986 (Box 1)
  - Gattorno, Antonio and Isabel, 1947-1978 (Box 1)
  - Girona, Julio, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Goodall, Donald to Richard Shack (about Riverón; see also Shack, Richard), 1981 (Box 1)
  - Group of Latin American Artists (GALA) Material, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
  - Hidalgo, ? (illustrated letter), 1929 (Box 1)
  - Hughes, Langston, 1931 (Box 1)
  - John Heller Gallery, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Lazaro, Angel, 19427, 1973, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Losado, Jorge, 1978-1983 (Box 1)
  - Lozano, Alfredo, 1967-1988, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Maribona, Armando, 1951, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Marinello, Juan, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Massaguer, Conrado W., 1935, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Matiz, Leo, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Meilach, Dona Z., 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Miami Herald and Vida, 1973, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Morandeyra, Mary, 1971 (Box 1)
  - La Nacion Newspaper, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - O'Brien de Lacy de Burickas, Nelly, undated (Box 1)
  - Padilla, Manuel Castro, Union Mexican de Autores, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Prohias, Antonio, [1975-1984], (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Pujol, R. A., 1952 (Box 1)
  - Ramirez, Eduardo Aviles, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Rebajes, Francisco, 1943-1985, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Rebajes, Frank and Pauline, 1952, 1960-1983, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Reed, Alma, 1935-1965 (Box 1)
  - Reyes, Alfonso, 1926 (Box 1)
  - [Riverón, Enrique], 1918-1925, 1948, undated, (handwritten note and postcards) (Box 1)
  - Roselló, ?, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Salazar, Toño, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Sandri, Alberto C., 1930 (Box 1)
  - Salinas, Baruj, 1976-1983 (Box 1)
  - Salinas, Baruj, Cousin of, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Sanchez, Guillermo, 1977, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Shack, Richard (see also Donald Goodall), 1981 (Box 1)
  - Sicre, José Gómez, 1959-1985, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Sicre, Juan José, 1967-1972 (Box 1)
  - Simoni, John P., 1965 (Box 1)
  - Townsend, Leo, Modern Screen Magazine, 1936, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified Individuals, 1952, 1959, undated (Box 1)
  - Various Individuals, 1918-1985, undated (Box 1)
  - Vida (see Miami Herald (Box 1)
  - Vilá, H. Portell (includes illustrated letters), [1969-1974] (Box 1)
  - Velix, F. R., 1936 (Box 1)
  - Wanguemert, [Luis Gomez], 1941-1960 (Box 1)
  - Wooden, Howard, Wichita Art Museum, 1979-1982, 1990, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Yunkers, Adya, 1960-1967, 1984, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Letters signed by Riverón, José Ramon Garcia, Pedrosa and Guillermo Martinez Marquez concerning start of a magazine, 1978, undated (Box 1)
- Writings, 1923-1980s, undated, Series 3:; (box 1, 0.2 ft.)
  Writings by Riverón found here primarily constitute his recollections of his trips to Paris and Madrid, and of the people he met in Latin America, Europe and the United States including Josephine Baker, Langston Huges, Federico Garcia Lorca, Kiki de Montparnasse, Mario Moreno [Cantinflas], Pablo Picasso, and Walter Pidgeon. The series also includes poetry, notes on art and film projects, childhood recollections and scattered diary entries, including an entry about Riverón's father's visit from Cuba in 1947.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by the subject Riverón writes about or the title of a piece of writing. One of the folders contains poems written by Ramon Rebajes for Riverón which is interfiled alphabetically by Rebajes last name.
  - Art, 1960s-1980s (Box 1)
  - Baker, Josephine1969 (Box 1)
  - Benavente, Jacinto, 1969 (Box 1)
  - [Cantinflas] Mario Moreno, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Childhood, circa 1980 (Box 1)
  - de Montparnasse, Kiki, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Don Senén Y Jacobito, by Riverón, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Garcia, Victor Manuel, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Gomez de la Serna, Ramon, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Hughes, Langston, 1969 (Box 1)
  - John Smith in Mexico, Essay by Riverón, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Lorca, Federico Garcia, 1969 (Box 1)
  - The Mind's Potential, Essay by Riverón, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1950, undated (Box 1)
  - El Nuevo Herald, Handwritten Essay, undated (Box 1)
  - Paris Trip, circa 1985 (Box 1)
  - Picasso, Pablo, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Pidgeon, Walter, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Poems, 1930s, 1972-1975, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Poem to [Julio] De Diego, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Rebajes, Ramon, Poems Written for Riveróncirca 1930s (Box 1)
  - Recuerdos de Un Viage a Isla Anglesa, [1947] (Box 1)
  - Rubenstein, Helen, 1969 (Box 1)
  - "Seven White Birds" Idea for Film, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Sketch of Rome, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Social Gatherings in Madrid, 1931, undated (Box 1)
  - Sunset on the Beach, 1970 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks, 1920s-1990s, undated, Series 4:; (boxes 1, 3, and 4, 0.7 ft.)
  Scrapbooks found in this series contain clippings, printed cartoons and illustrations, photographs, and reviews of exhibitions from the United States and Latin American newspapers.
  - Scrapbook, [1924-1926] (Box 1)
  - Dismantled Scrapbook of Cartoon Illustrations for Cine-Mundial and Other Magazines, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
  - Dismantled Scrapbook of Caricatures for Cine-Mundial and Bally Hoo,1930s-1940s (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks of Cartoons and Caricatures, 1940s (Box 1)
  - Dismantled Scrapbook of Caricatures on Photo Paper, undated (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1930s-1960s (Box 3 (sol))
  - Scrapbook, 1950s-1990s (Box 3 (sol))
  - Scrapbooks, 1920s-1930s (Box 4 (sol))
  - Scrapbook, 1922-1941 (Box 4 (sol))
  - Scrapbook, 1930s-1950s (Box 4 (sol))
- Artwork, 1958-1983, undated, Series 5:; (boxes 1 and 5, 0.4 ft.)
  - Original Color Drawing of Riverón by Unknown Artist, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Birthday Card by Riverón, 1978 or 1983 (Box 1)
  - Africanismo Calido, Handmade Book with Original Illustrations by Riverón, undated (Box 5 (sol))
- Printed Material, circa 1930-1992, Series 6:; (boxes 2 and 5, 0.7 ft.)
  Printed Material found here includes exhibition announcements and catalogs, clippings, and magazines such as Cine Mundial and Bally-Hoo featuring Riverón's caricatures.
  - Clippings, ca, 1930s-1983, undated, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Periodicals with Articles Mentioning Riverón, 1966-1967, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Clippings about Riverón Including The Miami Reporter, 1987, 1992, undated (Box 2)
  - Articles by Riverón, 1936, undated (Box 2)
  - Clippings Concerning Poetry Contest in which Riverón Participated, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Magazines Containing Riverón's Work or Reviews of his Work, 1932-1981, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Exhibition Invitations and Catalogs to Solo Exhibitions, 1936-1987, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Exhibition Invitations and Catalogs for Group Shows with Riverón,1931-1990s, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Exhibitions Invitations and Catalogs for Other Artists, 1945-1961, undated (Box 2)
  - Periodical, Modern Hispanic Magazine, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Publication, Dance International 1937-1938, Featuring Riverón Painting, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Illustration of Hollywood Celebrities, 1938 (Box 2)
  - School of the Wichita Art Association Calendars, 1949-1955 (Box 2)
  - Cartoons/Illustrations for Cine Mundial, 1932-1938, undated (Box 2)
  - Cartoons/Illustrations for Cine Mundial and Others, 1931-1934, 1957, undated (Box 2)
  - Magazine Articles About Riverón's Caricatures, 1947-1965 (Box 2)
  - Restaurant Menus Illustrated by Riverón, 1937, 1944, 1957, undated (Box 2)
  - Magazines with Riverón Caricatures and Illustrations, 1943-1947 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Caricatures of Movie Actors Printed in Modern Screen Magazine, 1938 (Box 5 (sol))
- Photographs, 1918-1992, undated, Series 7:; (boxes 2, 5, and 6, 0.6 ft.)
  This series contains photographs of Riverón, his wife Noella, his first wife Adria Delhortt Riverón, and others including Cundo Bermudez, Mario Carreño, Xavier Cugat, Ray Milland, Mario Moreno [Cantinflas], Pablo Neruda, Jose Clemente Orozco, Amelia Pelá, Alma Reed, Rosalind Russell, Juan José Sicre, David Alfaro Siqueiros, Rufino Tamayo, and Peláez Waguemert.
  Photographs are arranged by subject and then chronologically.
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1931-circa 1980, (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - Photographs of A. Lozano's Artwork (3) and Invitation to Lozano Exhibition, 1971-1972, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Riverón, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Riverón, Family, and Friends, circa 1918-1930s, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Riverón, Family, and Friends, 1930s-1980s, (8 folders) (Box 6 (hol))
  - Photographs of Riverón, Family, and Friends, Unidentified and undated, (2 folders) (Box 6 (hol))
  - Photographs of Riverón, undated (Box 5 (sol))
  - Photographs of Hollywood Set "Life Is A Stage," 1935 (Box 5 (sol))
  - Photographs of Riverón and Scenes of Cuba, 1952, 1964, undated (Box 5 (sol))
- Miscellany, 1927-1989, undated, Series 8:; (box 6, 7 folders)
  - Check Stubs from Contract Work for Caricatures, 1927-1928 (Box 6 (hol))
  - Riverón's File on Ramon Arroyo, Clippings of Caricatures, 1983 (Box 6 (hol))
  - Riverón's File on Mario Carreño, 1969, 1980-1989 (Box 6 (hol))
  - Riverón's File on Juan José M. Casado, 1977, 1987, undated (Box 6 (hol))
  - Riverón's File on A. Gattorno, 1975, 1979-1980 (Box 6 (hol))
  - Riverón's File on Antonio Prohias, 1978, undated (Box 6 (hol))
  - Announcement of Juan José Sicre's Death, undated (Box 6 (hol))